in our last session we saw how the whole
question of metaphysics is
interconnected with the science of
epistemology
how do we know what's really out there
and I show the strengths and weaknesses
of deduction and induction
and we ended up by looking at another
problem that the philosophers of the
18th century and the scientists of the
same era were encountering namely the
world was growing bigger and yet of a
different perspective the world was
growing smaller
I think about this sometimes on the golf
course I've had many experiences
where I've hit my tee shot where you're
not supposed to hit your tee shot in the
rough and I'll find my ball and I'll see
that in order to advance from where I am
to the green I have to negotiate a great
big tree that's blocking my Avenue to
the green
and I don't know how many times I've
been playing golf and and I'll look at
my situation I'm trying to figure out
how to invent a shot to go around the
tree either this way or that way or cut
the ball and hit it over the tree
because I know I can't hit it under the
tree although I can hit it under the
branches if I Hood the club face and get
a low shot I mean do that sort of thing
but as I'm sitting there you know
pondering my problem invariably who's
ever playing golf with me will say oh RC
go ahead just hit it trees are 90
percent air anyway have you ever heard
that expression trees are 90 air I don't
know whoever did the percentage analysis
of the makeup and composition of trees
that are in the rough at the golf course
but I hear this actually all the time
they're 90 air and then I have my
Colombo routine and I said well just a
minute there's one thing I don't
understand here and that is housecom I
can't hit the ball from here
towards that tree
and get through it 90 of the time it
doesn't sure doesn't seem like 90
percent of that tree is air
well actually if we got technical about
it
we would have to conclude that the
figure 90 percent is really not an
accurate estimate of the substance of
that tree
in fact it would be
way too small
did I say too small
or did I mean too high
no I mean too low
at least in terms of modern theories of
matter
and of substance
we have what we call the atomic theory
of reality
and we say that all these things
including the trees are made up of these
tiny little bits of atoms which have put
the atoms together and they'll make
molecules and so on
but recently I read a book on on physics
which was trying to give us some idea
of what
an atom looks like and you've all seen
the models of atoms that look like
little tops spinning and at the center
of the atom is a nucleus and then
spinning around in orbit around there
are these electrons or protons or
whatever they are that are flying around
outside from the nucleus and presumably
what's in between
is what space
not even air
less dense
than air
and the model I saw was of
the area of metropolitan
Los Angeles
they took the huge Outer Perimeter
of the city of Los Angeles and they said
imagine having an old VW
bug
that was parked
in this very center of downtown Los
Angeles
and there was nothing else in the city
no cars no buildings no people no trees
nothing just this single lone little VW
Bug
and you don't get to anything solid or
material until you get out to the outer
limits of the city
but everything in between the outer
limits of Los Angeles and the VW bug in
the middle
is space
that was the image that was used to
describe the composition of an atom
so obviously this represents far less
than one percent of all of this
and so if trees are 90 air
by this kind of reasoning the city of
Los Angeles is 99.9 percent
space
because it's simply made up
of atoms this is what I meant when I
said the world is getting smaller and
smaller and smaller to us
and this compounds the problem of
metaphysics
because if I say to you that 99 of what
you perceive
is empty space
not a whole lot really there
because it seems when I look at a person
or I look at a an object a physical
object it seems to me to be a hundred
percent solid
but when we look at it under a
microscope
and an atomic microscope
we find that there is precious little
extension to use Descartes term
or solidity
that's really there
now let's make the problem even more
egregious I need some help now to give
this following illustration Roger can
you come up here and help me for just a
second I'm not going to do anything you
know I'm not going to hurt you I just
want you to stand here and be my partner
for a second everybody now can see my
buddy Roger amundsen he's one of my star
students in this course in philosophy
now I would like the audience that is
here to tell me
what color
Roger's shirt is
how many think it's blue you all said
it's blue Roger they all said you had a
blue shirt you like his blue shirt it's
a nice blue shirt okay see that wasn't
hard wasn't Rush thank you buddy okay
we've all had the experience now of
seeing Roger's shirt and we all
identified
his shirt as being blue
now I can ask the question very simply
is Roger's shirt blue
yes okay
well
this is what
the philosophers of the 18th century
were very much concerned about
if I say Roger's shirt is blue
as soon as I use the word is
I'm using a form of the verb to be
I am predicating to his shirt something
about its being
I'm saying that the being or the essence
of this shirt
includes whatever else it includes the
quality
of blueness or color
now suppose we turned out all the lights
in here
and and added to that
we shut it our we shut it
add to that that we shut our eyes
would Roger's shirt
still be blue
or to put it another way is the blueness
of the shirt
something that is in the shirt
or is it something that I see as blue
because when light hits that object that
he's wearing
certain aspects of the spectrum of light
are absorbed by the material
and another aspect is reflected by the
material
and I only see
that element of the spectrum of light
that is blue
but without the source of the light
shining
there wouldn't be any color
because the color's not in the shirt
the colors in the light
now I look at the shirt and it looks
like the shirt has this quality of
blueness
when in fact the blue Nest is not part
of the essence of the shirt
and when we said the shirt is blue
at the metaphysical level
we made a mistake
now this is the kind of thing that John
Locke and his successors
were wrestling with that the more we
understood
about the world outside of us things
like light
and the secrets of the minute that we
discover microscopically
it changes our thinking of what we
believe really is out there
oh I'm not denying that there is such a
thing as light
or I'm nor am I denying that that shirt
and when I look at it
manifest the quality of blueness now
again we turn back the lecture clock a
few lectures back to when we looked at
Thomas Aquinas
and we looked at Thomas aquinas's view
of metaphysics and we said at that time
that according to Saint Thomas
every object
is made up of its substance
or its essence
and its accidents
and the accidents we said were the
external perceivable
qualities do you remember that
the qualities that we observe
or that we meet with our senses
now of course Thomas assumed
that the accidents of a thing are
inseparably related though distinguished
from its substance
now when John Locke was working on this
question
of perception and learning through the
senses
he made a distinction
between what he called primary qualities
and secondary qualities
and the distinction was this
primary qualities
are those qualities
that are really there
objectively inherent in the substance of
a thing
that there are certain qualities that
are found in shirts or in chalk or in
books or in people
one such inherent quality going back to
uh
Descartes was the quality of extension
that all material things are extended so
all material things have the primary
quality of extension
or we can speak of hardness but then
when you get to the level of color
or taste
or aroma
these other aspects that we encounter
with our five senses whenever we see
something or perceive something in the
external world
some of those things are added
by our mind or by the presence of light
or whatever
those would be what Locke called
secondary qualities
qualities that are not essential to the
reality
let me say it again qualities that
aren't part of the essence just as I've
said blueness is not an inherent
attribute of that shirt
blueness is something that is added by
my eye when I look at the shirt with the
addition of light is everybody follow
that okay
now with that Discovery or with that
distinction
what Locke was saying is
that there are real Essences there
metaphysical realities
and we perceive the substratum
of being
we have a perception of objective
reality
but that perception that we have is
mixed between our perception of
qualities that are really inherently in
the object
plus those
qualities that are added by the mind
or by the eyes or by the senses as we
perceive you've heard the old adage
Beauty
is in the eye
of the beholder
that is those who argue that point say
that there's no such thing as objective
Beauty
there may be something that is an object
that I look at and you look at and I say
is beautiful and you say is ugly
because the quality of beauty is
something that I am bringing to the
experience and I'm making a subjective
judgment or evaluation about something's
Beauty
or ugliness now that's the realm of
normal daily life where we meet up with
this kind of philosophical problem
no
following John Locke's work as a Pioneer
here
there came a very strange
philosopher strange in the sense of the
ideas that he represented
who was very much concerned about the
growing view of people in the 17th and
18th century towards materialism
and consequently toward atheism
and the man I'm talking about was a man
who was a bishop
of the Anglican Church
and his name was George Barkley is how
it's pronounced
oh I I never spell it right
but if you look at it you think it reads
Berkeley because it's spelled like the
University campus that we have in
California that we pronounce Berkeley
but the pronunciation of his name is
Barkley and he was born in 1685
and he died in 1753.
so his work really takes us into the
middle of the 18th century there are
those for example who believe that
Bishop Barkley's philosophy had a
profound influence on America's greatest
philosopher who of course
was Jonathan Edwards
but in any case Barclay's concern
remember we said if we're going to
understand a philosopher we have to ask
what problem is he trying to solve
what concern is he wrestling with
well being a bishop of the church
Barkley was concerned that science was
moving more and more and more away from
God
and more and more and more towards a
metaphysical view that said what is
ultimately real is not God
but matter itself
and that the universe is nothing more
and nothing less than a some experience
of material things
and
this became the bridge
in Barclays day for the whole kind of
Revival of atheism
and the atheist said we don't need to
postulate some Supernatural spiritual
being to explain the universe and to
explain our significance
the only thing that is real
is matter
there is no spirit and if there is no
Spirit realm then there is no room for
God
so Barkley is concerned not only as a a
philosopher but chiefly as a theologian
to rescue modern civilization
from this rushing tide of materialism
which brings in its wake
atheism
and he wants to see a scientific
Paradigm or model that has a real place
for God
now we will see in our next session how
Barkley approaches this problem and how
he looks at the distinction that Locke
made between primary and secondary
qualities and how the bishop would
wrestle with the question of Rogers blue
shirt or my problem was the tree that is
90 percent air that I encounter on the
golf course but we'll look at that in
our next session